<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>olf&#x27;s Computer Zoo</title>
    <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo" />
    <updated>2018-12-01T17:25:47+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Olaf Püschel</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Miscellaneous</title>
        <author>
            <name>Olaf Püschel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/miscellaneous.html"/>
        <id>https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/miscellaneous.html</id>
            <category term="misc"/>

        <updated>2018-11-30T16:11:09+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/teletype-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                    As no one sponsors a heated storehouse for me, I have to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/teletype-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                <div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">As no one sponsors a heated storehouse for me, I have to cram everything in my flat. Unfortunately this leads to "storing" the not so interesting computers under the desks.</div>
<div class="bbody" align=""> </div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h2 class="title"><a name=""></a>Now, whats lying there...</h2>
<div class="indent"> </div>
<ul>
<li class="listitem">Siemens PC-X, 80186, 1MB RAM, disk (small), text screen, runs SINIX 1.0 <br><em>Unfortunately only said "click" on the last power on.</em></li>
<li class="listitem">Commodore 900, Zilog Z8001, 1MB RAM, 20MB MFM disk, text screen, runs Coherent</li>
<li class="listitem">Apple II Clone,1(?) MHz 6502, 48kB RAM, mono screen, no disks :-(</li>
<li class="listitem">Commodore VC-20, 1(?) MHz 6502, 4(?)kB RAM, Datasette</li>
<li class="listitem">Commodore C=64, 1(?) MHz 6510, 64kB RAM, 1541 Floppy</li>
<li class="listitem">Schneider Euro-PC, 4.77Mhz 8088, 640kB RAM, 20MB MFM disk, 360kB floppy disk, mono screen</li>
<li class="listitem">Epson QX-10, 4(?) MHz Z80, 128kB RAM, 4(!) floppy disk, mono screen</li>
<li class="listitem">DEC LA-36 Teletype, 110 and 300 Baud</li>
<li class="listitem">Phillips P3800, "Lan-in-a-box", 4 80186 processors (1 master, 3 slaves) one per terminal, 70(?) MB disk, 60MB QIC tape, floppy disk, integrated UPS, 4 P2772 terminals <br><em>Unfortunately still untested.</em></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="para">
<div class="title"> </div>
<div class="title"><a name=""></a>And in the shelves ...</div>
<div class="indent"> </div>
<ul>
<li class="listitem">A Siemens Newton, identical to the Apple Newton Messagepad 100 except for the logo.</li>
<li class="listitem">A Amstrad Notepad NC100, Z80, full-size kyboard, 8-line LCD display.</li>
</ul>
<div class="hpanel">
<div class="illu" align=""> </div>
<div class="illu" align="">
<div class="gallery"   >
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/diskpack.jpeg" ><img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/diskpack-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="" width="240" height="240"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">DEC Diskpack 500MB</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/nc100.jpeg" ><img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/nc100-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="" width="240" height="240"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Amstrad NC100 Notepad</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/newton.jpeg" ><img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/newton-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="" width="240" height="240"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Siemens Newton</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/teletype.jpeg" ><img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/7/gallery/teletype-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="" width="240" height="240"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">DEC LA-36 Teletype</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<a href="images/diskpack.jpeg"><img src="images/s-diskpack.jpeg" border="0"></a>
<div class="capt" lang="en"> </div>
</div>
<div class="illu" align=""> </div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h2 class="title"><a name=""></a>And thats all?</h2>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Clearly no. Thats one the computers. There also are printers, terminals, calculators, parts and lots of paper. And, of course, the <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/8">yellow cable</a>.</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Apple Mac</title>
        <author>
            <name>Olaf Püschel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/apple-mac.html"/>
        <id>https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/apple-mac.html</id>
            <category term="mac"/>
            <category term="apple"/>
            <category term="68k"/>

        <updated>2018-12-01T17:24:33+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/6/mac-fron-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Apple Mac 128k Hey, there is a handle to throw it away!Who throws&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/6/mac-fron-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                <div class="para">
<h2 class="title">Apple Mac 128k</h2>
<div class="indent"> </div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Hey, there is a handle to throw it away!</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Who throws away a compact Mac? These small devices have the charme of simplicity, the advantage of being practical and the luxury of the pretty.
<p> </p>
A compact Mac - and the 128k was the grandfather of the line and the first Mac at all - does not occupy more desk space than a phone directory - an US one of course. This was one of the design targets. And if even this is too much one day, you just unplug the power cord, grab keyboard and mouse with one hand and the Mac in the other - utilizing the handle - and place it elsewhere.
<p> </p>
This Mac has been upgraded over time, so its decorated with a 512k label, but inside are 1024k - one full megabyte.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>And if you don't place it in a corner?</h3>
<div class="illu" align="">The 9" screen (1.bit per pixel, so black or white) with its 512x348 pixels is just sufficient to display te menu bar and one "big" window, in which you can work. But you can enjoy different fonts plus you can paint and draw.
<div class="capt" lang="en">
<p> </p>
<img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/6/mac-front.jpeg" alt="Mac 128k" width="785" height="523">My Mac likes most running with MacOS 6.7. That fits on one 800k disk together with MacWrite and MacDraw, and with a full Megabyte RAM working is quite comfortable. Data is stored on the second - external - floppy disk drive. Such luxury was untinkable when the first Mac system was shipped. Then it had one internal 400k disk (single sided, 3.5") and 128(!) kilobyte(!) memory. That way you spend one third of your time swapping disk. The previous owner changed the floppy drive, bought a second one and upgraded the ROM for supporting the double sided floppy disk drives and wrestled with the soldering iron to add more RAM.</div>
</div>
<div class="indent"> </div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>So whats so great about it?</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">The simple an intuitve use of hardware as well as software. One program runs at a time, the mouse has one button, the computer only one switch - not much you can get wrong.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>And the rest of the world...</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">... should have a serial interface. With these the Mac did all. Besides ports for mouse, keyboard and external disk drive the Mac sports two serial interfaces in RS-422 standard, to which you can connect RS-232 devices too.
<p> </p>
With them it does everything. Printing, modem, network ... and there's no other way because the system has no expansion slots. For the uninitiated user its even impossible to open the case, you need an "MacOpener" to do this. That leads to strange constructs like the HD20, a hard disk which gets plugged to the external drive port instead of the floppy. Performance is like you'd expect :-)</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h2 class="title">Powerbook 180 </h2>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>On the Road again...</h3>
<div class="illu" align=""><a href="images/pb180.jpeg"><img src="images/s-pb180.jpeg" border="0"><img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/6/pb180.jpeg" alt="Powerbook 180" width="900" height="675"></a> ... take your Powerbook with you. And while it carries the Power in its name, there is no PowerPC inside but an good old MC68030 with 33MHz. With around 6.5 pounds it still is in the weight range for notebooks, allright, at the upper limit.</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h2 class="title"><a name=""></a>The ball rolls!</h2>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">The full-size tarckball refreshingly differs from the moderen touchpads and rubber gimmicks and offers a superb mouse surogate. I had  acquired an extra mouse, but never plugged it in. Mounting the trackpad is possible because of the relative height of the device, at least the whole ball has to fit in - one half in the top, the other in the bottom shell. Above and below the two buttons are arranged, both with the same functions as the Mac mouses with a single button. This way you can use the one which fits your personal handling best. The mouse pointer moves about a LCD with 640x480 pixels, able to display four levels of gray with a backlight. The keyboard is nice to type on and has - thank to the thickness of the case - an acceptable key lift.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Plugging Games</h3>
<div class="illu" align="left"><a href="images/pb180-if.jpeg"><img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/6/pb180-if.jpeg" alt="Powerbook connectors" width="900" height="358"><img src="images/s-pb180-if.jpeg" border="0"></a>In extensibility the Powerbook shows its a real Apple. Difficult to exotic. There is an internal slot for a modem, which I own, but somehow it's not working. Otherwise the are the usual suspects: ADB for mouse and keyboard, an exotic port for an external display and two serial ports for printer and modem. No infrared, no PCMCIA and regretably no Ethernet. But there is a SCSI interface, with an strange and space saving HDI format. For data exchange Apple threw in a floppy disk drive - of course with motorised eject as it suits an Apple.</div>
<div class="indent"> </div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Weak hinges</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">This special Powerbook suffers from widespread desease. The strong springs holding the upper shell tend to tear out the holding blocks of the screws which are only pressed in. This can be mended with melt-glue, but that had already been tried with my one, so I had to choose a more radical approach. Drill two hole on the right and left side into the shell, and now you can use two two matching screws to attach it tightly to the clapping mechanics. The method might not be the most aestetical pleasing but has the advantage of being simple and succesful.</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="footer"> </div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>DEC Multia VX40</title>
        <author>
            <name>Olaf Püschel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/dec-multia.html"/>
        <id>https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/dec-multia.html</id>
            <category term="risc"/>
            <category term="dec"/>
            <category term="alpha"/>

        <updated>2018-11-30T16:18:36+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/5/multia-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Alpha GenerationThe Multia is a relativly modern and fast machine. With a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/5/multia-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                <div class="para">
<h2 class="title">Alpha Generation</h2>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">The Multia is a relativly modern and fast machine. With a 166 MHz 21066 Alpha processor the machine shows an integer performance comparable to a 100 MHz Pentium, the float performance even higher.</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<div class="illu" align=""><a href="images/multia.jpeg"><img src="images/s-multia.jpeg" border="0"></a> </div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>But thats the ultimate personal workstation!</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align=""><img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/5/multia.jpeg" alt="DEC Multia" width="862" height="623">Right. And this is the smallest and slowest version. There are machines in the same enclosure with 266 MHz processors and larger disks (you can mount a frame for a 3.5" disk instead of the PCI slot)
<p> </p>
Unfortunately the machine basically flopped. Targeted as a client system with Windows-NT (yes Windows once ran on Alphas as well as on MIPS and PowerPC), the concept was refused by the market. The corresponding Pentium line didn't gather a larger following either.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Who wants NT on his box anyway...</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Oh, Linux and OpenBSD run on these boxes too. I already tried Linux, BSD to follow. At the moment it is doomed with NT3.51, 4.0 is available too (but mine only sports 24MB RAM, which is a little tight).</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Besides</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">... it bugging me! The 19" monnochrome display loitering here was to be connected to the Multia. It is fixed frequency, and there are jumpers to tell the Multias to show the console with - for instance - 1152x900@66Hz. Thats fine with the display. Unfortunately the two disagree about the polarity of the V-Sync signal, so there is not steady image ... sight. If I knew which bit to set or clear - then I could modify the startup script of the boot monitor ...</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>DECstation 5000</title>
        <author>
            <name>Olaf Püschel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/decstation.html"/>
        <id>https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/decstation.html</id>
            <category term="risc"/>
            <category term="mips"/>
            <category term="dec"/>

        <updated>2018-12-01T17:25:23+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/3/decstation-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                    DEC? Thats the VMS people, right?Right. VMS on VAXen has been DECs&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/3/decstation-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                <div class="para">
<h2 class="title">DEC? Thats the VMS people, right?</h2>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Right. VMS on VAXen has been DECs cash cow for a long time. With the raise of the RISC processors in the beginning 80's also DEC began to look for an alternative to VCISC (Very Complex Instruction Set Computer). An effort to create an in-house processor (PRISM) fizzled, but should laster have critical influence on the Alpha development. But first it was decided to use MIPS R-line processors. The machines where designed from ground up to run the DEC variant of UNIX - Ultrix. There is no VMS Port.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h2 class="title">The little sister - DECstation 5000/120</h2>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">My DECstation 5000/120 is from the middle of the line. In means of time - no R2000 anymore and not yet a R4000 - as well as in means of power - there is the personal DECstation and the 200 line models. With the R3000 processor running at 20MHz and supported by a R3010 numerical processor the machine delivers abount 30 MIPS. This is much compared to the Sun-3 line, about as much as the SPARCstation-1 and not much compared with modern workstations with their several hundred MIPS.
<p> <img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/3/decstation.jpeg" alt="DECstation 5000/120" width="900" height="640"></p>
The machine is built into a metal enclosure about 19x15x2 inch. Besides the power supply there is a logic board with three TURBOchannel slots running at 12.5 MHz inside. Then we have the CPU module (upgradable to 33MHz or R4000), two bays for 3.5" disks and one externaly accessible 5.25" bay. One TURBOchannel slot is occupied by the PMAGB-B, displaying his 1280x1024 pixel in 256 colours at 72Hz on a 19" colour screen.
<p> </p>
In addition there are two serial ports, the SCSI-2 port and Ethernet AUI. Workstations attaching the console to a serial port if no keyboard is connected is not uncommon. But when the serial ports are labeled <em>2</em> and <em>3</em> and the terminal has to be attached to the one marked <em>3</em> this definitively is a DEC special.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h2 class="title">The Big Brother - DECstation 5000/150</h2>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">The model 150 is the fastest in the 100 line. Equipped with a R4000, clocked at 50 MHz, it is considerable faster than the R3000 models. It is only outperformed by the model 260, the top of the 200 line. This one not only has a TURBOchannel clock at 25 MHz, double the speed of the 100s, but also a R4400 processor which gives a remarlable power boost. Aside the processor the model 150 does not differ from the model 120. This web server is running on the 5000/150 with NetBSD</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title">Type &lt;ESC&gt;:q&lt;CR&gt; to quit vi</h3>
<div class="indent">Not too simple, as the trusted LK401 keyboard shows Ø and Æ, but now ESC key can be found. Ultrix maps F11, what's at least inventive. Here ESC gets merciless mapped to F1, that in the right place anyhow.<span class="hspace"><a href="images/decmouse-top.jpeg"><img src="images/s-decmouse-top.jpeg" border="0"></a></span><span class="hspace"><a href="images/decmouse-bottom.jpeg"><img src="images/s-decmouse-bottom.jpeg" border="0"></a></span></div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<div class="illu" align="">
<h3 class="capt" lang="en">Top and bottom of the DEC mouse</h3>
</div>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">The mouse differs from other mice too. It is mechanical buthas no ball. Instead two rubber disks are mounted in a way that each has onepoint on the diameter resting on the pad.</div>
<div class="bbody" align=""><img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/3/decmouse-top.jpeg" alt="DEC Puck Mouse" width="150" height="179"><img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/3/decmouse-bottom.jpeg" alt="DEC Puck Mouse/Bottom" width="150" height="180"></div>
<div class="bbody" align="">So the motion component along the tangent to this point turns the disk. The disks are aranges in a manner that one captures teh X- and the other the Y-component of the movement. In addition the mouse is circular.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title">Now, what is that ULTRIX?</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Simply DEC port of good old BSD 4.2 (of course with DEC extension). Here I have ULTRIX 4.5 running, the last available version. Since I hit the one time to often I'll start to collect <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/4" title="ULTRIX Tipps &amp; Tricks">ULTRIX Tips &amp; Tricks</a>. Inovative is DECs own window manager <em>dxwm</em>, you can start instead of MOTIF, making the windows look like on a VAX with VMS.</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>DEC MicroVAX</title>
        <author>
            <name>Olaf Püschel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/dec-vaxstations.html"/>
        <id>https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/dec-vaxstations.html</id>
            <category term="vax"/>
            <category term="dec"/>
            <category term="cisc"/>

        <updated>2018-11-30T16:25:11+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/2/vax-term-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                    DEC? Thats the VMS people, right?Exactly. The VAX is the peak of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/2/vax-term-detail.jpeg" alt="" />
                <div class="para">
<h2 class="title">DEC? Thats the VMS people, right?</h2>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Exactly. The VAX is the peak of the CISC architecture, and runs happily with VMS. The VAXen family is widespread, from desktop machines to multi-rack monsters. The MicroVAX is a later model and belongs - even at sight - to the smaler VAXen. While the CPUs of the earlier models - like the calssic VAX 11/780 - filled multiple boards, the VAX architecture has been cramed on a chip in a CMOS implementation for the MicroVAXen. The chip called CVAX runs at 10MHz in the 3300 and as 1kB(!) cache attached. The memory is luxuriosly equipped with 4MB - VAX machine code is extremely dense.
<p><img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/2/vax-term.jpeg" alt="MicroVAX 330" width="317" height="592"> </p>
To be able to realize the CVAX chip with the then contemporary technology, DEC utilized a trick: The CPU implements only the most common instructions of the VAX instruction set - the rest triggers a trap, and is implemented in software. </div>
<h3 class="bbody">Square, nice and handy.</h3>
</div>
<div class="para">
<div class="illu" align=""><a href="images/vax-term.jpeg"><img src="images/s-vax-term.jpeg" border="0"></a>Even mechanicaly the 3300 stands out from the masses - which computer looks like a flower stand. The base of the case is nearly square, with casters on the bottom. With about three feet height, you could easily pace a flower pot or a vase atop.
<div class="capt" lang="en">
<p> </p>
But a terminal comes in nicely - my VT-320 gets along well with the VAX. Meanwile I got hold of a keyboard with US layout, what eases up things noticably, compared to German layout.
<p> </p>
The drive are located On the upper front behind the cover. To the left are two 300MB DSSI disks on thick rubber mounts. DSSI is a early, incompatible variant of SCSI. They are 5.25" devices in half height. There is space for one more.
<p> </p>
The front panel has an error LED, a write protect switch (with LED) and a ready switch (with LED) for each of the drives possible. Below are the Restart/Run and teh Halt push-button plus teh power LED.
<p> </p>
The front panel can be covered with a protective door of semi-transparent perspex, through wich the LEDs glow.</div>
</div>
<div class="indent"> </div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Compaq Tape? - CompacTape!</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Top right you see the CompacTape drive. These things are the grand-grandfathers of the modern DLT (Digital Linear Tape) drives. Full 90MB are packed on the tapes. The Media looks exactly like DLT tapes, so the mechanical specs did'nt change.</div>
<div class="bbody" align=""> </div>
<div class="bbody" align=""><img class="post__image--center" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/2/compactape.jpeg" alt="CompacTape" width="268" height="162"></div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<div class="illu" align="left"><a href="images/compactape.jpeg"><img src="images/s-compactape.jpeg" border="0"></a>The tape cartridge technologie is inventive. To save the room the empty reel would take up, only the would up tape is in the cartride. In front is an eyelet for tearing the tape out and threads it into the mechanics. Since this is afully complicated, you ougth to obey the right sequence when changing tapes: Press button, wait for LED to go dark, open lock, remove cartride, insert new one, close lock, press button, wait for LED to light steady, done.</div>
<div class="indent"> </div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>VMS is different</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Only VMS is possible as an operating system for this VAX at this time. NetBSD does not support the DSSI disks an the "classic" V7 binaries from DEC/Compaq/HP only like "classic" Hardware, in the directionof a VAX 11/750. That's hard for an <span class="trade">Unix</span> guy, because VMS is <strong>different</strong> ... sigh.
<p> </p>
For instance I was not able to shut down the machine cleanly in the beginning, also I already had found <em>shutdown.com</em>. How could I know that its a DCL script and thus has to be called as <strong>@shutdown</strong>. Meanwhile I found the docs on the net and borrowed a few paper manuals.
<p> </p>
Besides, VMS is extremely chatty. Options are prefixed with '/' (where have I seen this before?). This gives something like:</div>
<blockquote>
<div class="pre"><code>BACKUP/VERIFY/LOG *.LIS MFA0:LIST.BCK</code></div>
</blockquote>
<div class="bbody" align="">Saves all files of type LIS to drive MFA0 under the name LIST.BCK, with verify and log listing. Or, short <strong>gtar cvWf /dev/rmt0 *.lis</strong>
<p> </p>
On the other hand VMS can do several intersting things. The filesystem can manage different versions of each file inherently. The security meassures are manifold and sophisticated, as well as the accounting system.
<p> </p>
It even has a TCP/IP Stack, which is configured <em>different</em>, but meanwhile the machine is fully integrated in the network.</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="footer"> </div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Sun 3 Series</title>
        <author>
            <name>Olaf Püschel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/sun-microsystem-3-series.html"/>
        <id>https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/sun-microsystem-3-series.html</id>
            <category term="sun"/>
            <category term="cisc"/>
            <category term="68k"/>

        <updated>2018-11-30T16:39:52+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/1/sun3-60-datail.jpeg" alt="Sun Logo" />
                    Sun Microsystem Model 3/50 The Sun 3/60 is the big brother of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/1/sun3-60-datail.jpeg" alt="Sun Logo" />
                <div class="para">
<div class="indent">
<h2 class="bbody">Sun Microsystem Model 3/50</h2>
<p><img src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/1/sun3-50.jpeg" alt="Sun 3/50" width="650" height="488"></p>
<div class="bbody" align=""> </div>
<div class="bbody" align="">This Sun 3/50 was my first historical workstation and my first real workstation at all (Linux PCs don't count). The matching black and white monitor is on top (black pixels on white, not the exterior), in front lies the type-3 keyboard and the mouse with optical pad (about letter size). No chance to get away with less then nine square feet of desk space.
<p> </p>
The central unit is a big flat box (about 19x15x2 inches) with the Sun Logo as its only decoration. Inside is a power supply and a huge 15x15 inch board holding all the logic.</div>
</div>
<ul style="list-style-type: circle;">
<li class="listitem">MC68020 processor, 16Mhz, with MC68881 numerical processor</li>
<li class="listitem">The Sun memory management unit, enablib paging</li>
<li class="listitem">Four (!) MB RAM consisting of a muddle of soldered memory chips</li>
<li class="listitem">Ethernet interface with 10-Base-2 and AUI connectors</li>
<li class="listitem">Black and white graphics with 1152x900 pixels</li>
<li class="listitem">SCSI-1 interface, 2 RS-232 ports, keyboard und mouse port</li>
</ul>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Needs more RAM!</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">The 3/50 is a closed system and can't be extended - officially. Despite the people were not satisfied with the 4 MB RAM and so there are strange snap-on-boards, introducing a few SIMM sockets.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>What - no IDE interface?</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">While I have a disk subsystem for the machine, it ist not flying yet. It contains an Emulex ESDI-SCSI converter, whose logic board is able to attach two ESDI disks as LUN 0 and 1 of a SCSI-ID.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Through the yellow wire</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Nevertheless the 3/50 can be see in operation, thanks to net boot and <a href="#INTERNAL_LINK#/post/8">Yellow-Cable</a>. There even is a striped down SunOS-4 with an X11 server to use it as an X-Terminal. This task is mastered allright by the system.</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<div class="indent">
<h2 class="bbody">Sun Microsystem Model 3/60</h2>
<p class="bbody"><img class="post__image--right" src="https://olfp.github.io/computer-zoo/media/posts/1/sun3-60.jpeg" alt="Sun 3/60" width="804" height="566">The Sun 3/60 is the big brother of the 3/50. One third faster with 20 MHz and capable of being equiped with up to 24 1MB SIMMs (mine has 20 at the moment), it presents a much more powerfull machine. In addition there is the colour graphics addon board (1152x900 with 256 colours, at 67Hz, plugged int the P4 bus). A black-and-white graphics like in the 3/50 is integrated on the system board too. It can be user when the machine was purchased without color graphics or for dual screen operation.</p>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Mice and other Accessories</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">Peripherial connections, keyboard and mouse (including the letter sized pad) are identical to the 3/50. On top is a colour display of the classical breed - ultra heavy fishbowl.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>Bricks 'n stuff</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">It is accompained by a 300MB SCSI disk (5.25", full height) in a "Shoebox". Obviously the Sun folk have large feet, the thing is rather bulky. Unfortunately I am lacking the QIC-24 tape drive (60MB), which would fit in nicely.</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="para">
<h3 class="title"><a name=""></a>And what software? Solaris 9?</h3>
<div class="indent">
<div class="bbody" align="">At the moment SunOS 4.1.1 is installed on the disk, with SunView as graphical desktop. There is also X11 with OpenLook 2.0, but that eats up memory and the machine had only 12MB while installing. You can install X11/OpenLook on the 3/50 too, but the it takes 20 minutes to start the graphics.
<p> </p>
Sometime I will give a BSD (Open or Net) a try. This should make the 3/60 quite usable ;-)</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
